<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter from a gentleman in America, to his friend in Scotland</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 3 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87925</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1382A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R220796</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899993</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899993</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135560</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87925)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135560)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2502:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter from a gentleman in America, to his friend in Scotland</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Dated in text: Bolston [sic] November 8th. 1689. The "8" in "1689" has been altered in MS. to a "9".</note>
                  <note>Concerns "the shameful desertion of Caledonia".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the John Carter Brown Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Scotland --  History --  1689-1745 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Broadsides --  England</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:135560:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135560:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A LETTER FROM A Gentleman in <hi>AMERICA,</hi> to his Friend in <hi>SCOTLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>BOLSTON</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>November</hi> 8th. 1699.</date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Wrote to you from <hi>Jamaica,</hi> giving account of the Shameful Deſertion of <hi>Caledonia:</hi> I doubt not but long ere now, the Company is ſenſible of the true Cauſe, and hath taken Care to prevent the like for the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: It ſeems ſtrange, that Perſons of known Integrity, Courage, and Experience, could not be ſent and Commiſſionat for the Management of a Concern of ſo Great Importance. Whatever may be the Diſcourſe of their want of Proviſions, I know very well we have ſuch Friends in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, as contrary to any Proclamation or Prohibition, would have ſupplyed and may yet ſupply, the ſaid Colony, with all neceſſar Proviſions, if they have timely Notice and Encouragement from the Company.</p>
            <p>One of the two Ships that were ſent with a Supply of 300 Men, hath been at <hi>Caledonia,</hi> and is come to <hi>Jamaica:</hi> We long to hear of the Recruits expect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the <hi>Riſing-Sun:</hi> And hope when they Arrive, they may Re-ſettle the Place. Its alſo hoped for, and thought neceſſar, that the Company do not give over, as if no more were requiſit for ſecuring the Colony (Its well known the <hi>Spaniſh, French,</hi> and Others, will uſe all their Art, Fraud, and Force, to Hinder, Undermine, and Ruin it) but that they continue their Supplies of Men, Arms, <hi>&amp;c:</hi> untill they be Certified their Colony is beyond Danger from all their Enemies.</p>
            <p>We hope the great Loſs ſuſtained, ſhall not Diſcourage nor abate the Zeal of any Concerned: Such undertakings do not preſently Ripen and Enrich the Adventurers: What tho the Company ſee no Return for Seven Years? The Place is worth Ten times the Charge: And in time will fully re-imburſe them, if Mountains of Gold, or being the Staple of Trade for both ſides of <hi>America,</hi> can do it; Beſides the Bleſſing of Heaven, which we may expect to the Meſſengers of the glad Tidings of Salvation to People in Darkneſs.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:135560:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:135560:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
